Okay, so now we're
going to look at
different types of thumbnail
strategies that you're going
to try out to
get a click. And
our long -term goal
here really is to
find a thumbnail strategy,
basically a style that
works for our channel
and our viewers love.
And then when we
see that it works,
we repeat it as
close to as possible
as we can over
and over again. And
what you're going to
find is if you
look back on loads
of established channels, this
is exactly what they've
done. So let me
give an example. This
is my channel from
about a year ago.
And what I was
doing was trying lots
of different thumbnail styles
and strategies to try
and find the thing
that would then work.
I could go all
in on, which ended
up with really simple
designs like this. And
at the time of
filming this, this is
basically what my channel
looks like. I'm just
repeating something over and
over again when it
works. And then we
have Meadow, who I've
used as an example
from earlier. She started
off with all kinds
of different thumbnails, found
the thing that worked,
went all in on
it. And then we
have Charlie Morgan. He
had these really over
-designed. Kind of crypto
bro looking thumbnails. And
then he tried something
different and he started
getting hundreds of thousands
of views and growing
very quickly because he
then just repeated that
style and strategy over
and over again. So
the way that finding
the thumbnail strategy for
your channel works is
exactly the same as
everything else that we're
going to do. It's
by testing. We come
up with our minimum
viable thumbnail options. We
put them out. We
see what happens. And
then we take any
lessons we've learned into
the next one so
that over time we
keep improving. And we're
going to keep improving
and growing. All right.
So let's look at
the different thumbnail strategies
that you can use.
So this first one,
probably my favorite one
of all time. It's
my go to and
it's called cognitive dissonance.
So let me show
you what cognitive dissonance
looks like. So this
video here, if you
look at the thumbnail,
it says do not
buy a house. Now,
in the UK in
particular, we are told
you have to get
on the property ladder.
That's the best purchasing
decision you'll ever make.
So as a Brit,
I look at that
and I'm like, what?
That goes against everything
I thought to be
true. And then here
we've got Brian Johnson.
With breakfast pointing at
chocolate. Again, I was
told I should not
eat chocolate for breakfast.
That goes against everything
I thought to be
true. And then we
have Nisha telling me
to look poor. And
again, I'm like, what?
Why do I want
to look poor? That
goes against everything I
thought to be true.
So that is the
idea of a cognitive
dissonance thumbnail. You basically
use a thumbnail and
title to make people
curious by challenging what
they thought to be
true. So the thing
I love about this
is it raises curiosity
like crazy. And, you
know, we need curiosity
to get a click.
And also the pros
of it are it's
just so easy to
design. I mean, if
we look at these,
it's just text and
a face most of
the time. So we
don't have to do
anything complex. They also
make viewers incredibly curious
and they hit that
why, how and what
response hard. Now, the
cons can be very
hard to come up
with the words that
will go on your
thumbnail. But they are,
I would say, best
for absolutely any type
of channel. And my
advice for when to
use this is, well,
I probably try and
use it every video.
If you can, as
one of your thumbnail
options. OK, the next
star we have is
called the comparison. And
the comparison thumbnail is
pretty much just a
before and after where
you show the before
and then the result
the viewers want. So
you can see here
this guy was 275
pounds. He dropped it
to 175. That's the
result we want. Again,
we've got this visual
contrast and before and
after here. And these
videos are all very
successful because of it.
We can also see
this one. From living
leggings, a very simple
before and after this
one before and after
and then this one
before and after. So
this sort of thumbnail
visually demonstrates a dramatic
transformation. And the pros
of it are if
your result is very
clear in the after,
it kind of makes
the video more credible.
It also can make
viewers curious and it
hits that why, what
and how. Now, the
cons of this are
you need a visually
dramatic results. If you
don't have one, you
can't really use this.
This style of thumbnail
is probably best for
any kind of visual
niece. Fitness in particular.
This should be one
of your thumbnails you
test on every single
video. They're just so
powerful. Creative hobby niches,
DIY, any kind of
results focused. So when
should you use this?
Basically, if you have
a visual transformation that
you think viewers would
be hooked by. The
next type of thumbnail
we have is the
result. So the result
is pretty simply just
showing the result. So
we can see here
there's thumbnails got this
big amount of money
and the result is
people just want to
earn a lot of
money. We can see
Humphrey here. He's. Result
is 481 % faster
to a million. This
is a very simple
thumbnail because it's just
showing eye makeup. But
in this sense, that
is the result. The
viewer wants to do
that. I make up
like this and this
one is a result
because it's showing an
amazing looking cheesecake. And
again, that is what
the viewers want. And
then we got a
few more examples here.
So in the fitness
niche, the body is
what the viewers want.
And in this one,
we've got a YouTube
studio set up that
looks really cool. And
again, that's just what
the viewers want. So.
Results from now is
where you just kind
of show or tease
the outcome that your
viewers desire. And the
pros of this, you
have a really appealing
result in your thumbnail.
It raises your credibility.
If your audience is
looking for a solution
of some sort, this
is a fantastic option.
But another thing is
it's very good at
setting up expectations for
the viewer. And another
pro is, well, it
instantly in a visual
just communicates the benefit
of the video and
the result. Now, the
cons are if the
outcomes vague or kind
of unpopular. So if
you're convincing or your
result doesn't look that
good, you don't want
to use this. Now,
these are best for
educational channels, how to
channels, skill based niches,
audiences and any audience
that's seeking a solution.
And you basically use
this when you have
a result you want
to show off. The
next type of thumbnail
strategy is called social
hacking. So social hacking
is very powerful. It
can get you millions
of views because you
basically harness someone else's
credibility to get the
click. So let me
give an example. This
is one of my
old videos. Where I
made it about Marcus
Brownlee and Mr Who's
the Boss, two massive
YouTubers. And what that
means is people who
don't know, like or
trust me are more
likely to click on
them. So this is
a previous client who
used Taylor Swift to
social hack in his
image. This is James
Smith, another previous client
who, instead of using
a purse and used
Prime, the energy drink,
so you can social
hack with a brand
too. And this is
John, another previous client
who used a famous
producer. So I don't
know who that is,
but everyone in his
niche does. And that's
the thing. You basically
just want to try
and find something. Someone
that your viewers go,
wow, I love that
person or I'm super
interested in that thing
and then lead with
that in the thumbnail.
So the pros of
this are these things
can be rocket fuel
for channels like they
can really blow up
small channels quite fast.
However, be careful of
this.
If you go and
make a video about
like Mr Beast, you're
going to get Mr
Beast fans, not fans
of the topic. So
sometimes you can go
a bit too wide
and bring in the
wrong line of people,
which could potentially hurt
your channel. So you
can't just go and
make a video about
like Mr Beast, you're
going to get Mr
Beast fans, not fans
of the topic. So
you can't just go
and make a video
about like Mr Beast,
you're going to get
Mr Beast fans, not
fans of the topic.
Also, if you make
every video about someone
else, it's not great
for raising your own
credibility. So I wouldn't
use this type of
strategy for every video.
You can mix it
in with other types
of content, but just
be careful that you
don't become a channel
that's about other people
because it's not as
great for sales. Now,
this is great for
new and small channels
because you can just
blow up very quickly
doing it. It's also
an amazing strategy to
hop on a trend
or hop on a
news story. So if
there is someone in
your niche who does
something and reporters get
on it, you can
have your say on
it and harness that
trend and get a
ton of views. When
do you use it?
Basically, if you have
someone your viewers love
to watch. But just
keep in mind, the
person in the thumbnail
has to be really
well known and loved.
If you put someone
who's not that well
known, you might as
well put your own
face in it. All
right, the next style
of thumbnail is called
the curiosity. This is
very similar to the
cognitive dissonance, but it's
just about making people
curious rather than challenging
what they thought to
be true. So if
you're a fan of
the channel, you might
want to put your
own face in it.
For this example, they've
used this text which
says, this is a
lie, which instantly makes
you go, what is
a lie? You look
at the highlighted button
there and you think,
I've got an M
on my keyboard. Why
is that a lie?
And you want to
click. This example here,
I'm saying, delete this
from the timeline, which
makes people curious to
know, like, why should
I delete it? In
this thumbnail, I said,
quit everything. And then
you get this big
result. If you quit
everything, people want to
know, well, why should
you quit everything? And
then in this one
here, we've got a
stop sign pointing at
the guitar. People just
want to know why.
Why should I stop
doing whatever that guy's
doing? So the curiosity
is just focusing on
why, what, or how,
and trying to get
viewers to wonder that
as soon as they
see it. And the
pros of this are
they're really good for
a cold audience, new
audience. If they don't
know, like, or trust
you yet, you can
get them to click
just through sheer curiosity.
And it's probably one
of the most proven
strategies on YouTube for
thumbnails, along with the
cognitive dissonance and the
before and after contrast.
The cons, these can
be very clickbaity. So
you win. You're right.
And you're right. If
you're doing intros, which
I'll teach you how
to do, you really
got to make sure
you match the viewers
expectations that they think
they have before they
click. Otherwise, they won't
like you. They're also
very hard to come
up with. And you
will find that some
viewer types find it
tacky. Who are they
best for? I'd say
any type of creator
and when to use
them any time. All
right. The next style
of thumbnail is the
minimal. So the minimal
is basically a aesthetically
kind of pleasing or
very basic thumbnail image.
So we can see
in this first one.
here. This is a
cinematic video and we've
got this lens in
the middle and a
lovely photo. This video
here, there's not really
anything going on. There's
no text. It's just
kind of a pleasing
image on the eye.
And then this one,
it's nice and symmetrical.
It's a very well
-taken photo. And these
sort of images, they
basically appeal to people
who like that look,
that kind of authentic
style. So the pros
of these are these
images often look super
professional, so they raise
your credibility. Even if
they don't look professional
and they're just taken
with a webcam, they
kind of feel more
authentic. And the creative
viewer types tend to
love them. Okay, so
the cons. You've got
to be good at
photography and design. It's
very hard to make
a good -looking, simple
photo. So I personally
stay clear of them
for that reason. They
are much higher risk
for most businesses, I'd
say. Now, these are
really good, for the
creative niches, video, Photoshop,
photography, and also sometimes
the self -help channels.
But you can use
these for more vulnerable
moments. So if you've
got like a, I'm
tired and stressed video
and I'm thinking of
giving up, you usually
see someone on the
thumbnail like... Use them
when there's these vulnerable
moments you want to
talk about, or when
high production is needed.
But for most of
you, you can stay
clear. So Ed, which
one do I pick?
There's so many flipping
options. Well, the research
process, I'm going to
teach you, is going
to show you which
one you pick. But
you don't pick one.
We use our system.
We try different styles.
And over time, we
work out which is
the best style for
our viewers and then
repeat that. Okay, so
let's move on to
the next video where
I'm going to start
to teach you some
thumbnail design rules. Because
if you can't make
your image look good,
your strategy won't work
in the first place.